Hello, everybody, and
welcome to the first lecture
in our series of actual
lectures on renal physiology.
And the title of our
lecture is we're going to
start off with some
straightforward functional
anatomy and organization
of the urinary system
before we start going
into the intricate details
that are involved in the
function of the kidney.
The session objectives
are here, so we're going
to talk about the major
functions of the kidney,
the growth structures, and
their interrelationships.
Then we're going to go
a little bit narrower.
We're going to look at
the gomerular filtration
barrier, and then the
components of the duct
system and the nephron,
and then talk about
the JG apparatus and
its role in homeostasis,
and then finish off
by talking about the
control of urination,
but that really has
to do more with the
function of the kidney,
so it has to do more
with objective one.
So like always, let's start
off with a scenario. So
you start off your rotation
in EM. When a young woman,
teenager, is brought into
the ER by her parents,
she's an athlete, she's an
avid soccer player, she's
got no significant past
medical history, she's tall,
in shape, and she's
in acute distress.
When you see her, she
is curled up in the
fetal position in a
bed. She's nauseous,
She looks dehydrated,
and she's suffering.
She has deep
bilateral flank pain.
She's hardly urinating
in half a liter a day.
And the little bit
of urine you manage
to collect had
blood, substantial
amounts of blood,
protein, and glucose.
However, she's not diabetic.
Her plasma glucose is normal.
So you don't know
how to explain that.
You talk to her
parents and she is
health conscious and
loves social media.
And through some
something, they
tell you that she had gotten,
you know, based on some
social media influencer,
some fitness influencer,
she had ordered
some herbal teas from
a very famous European
spa and had just drunk
some of it. And you
wonder if there's a
cause and effect here.
So, herbal tea, deep
pain, lack of urine,
significant urinalysis.
What could they have and how
would the function,
knowing a little bit about
the functional anatomy
of the kidney, help you
describe the sequence of
symptoms following this?
So let's talk about the
kidney, and what does it
look like? Well, and what
it is? Well, this is the
functional anatomy of the
kidney, this slide here,
and the kidneys serve three
functions of important
one, filtration, removing
metabolic products and
toxins, and excreting them,
removal of waste products.
Second one is regulation
of fluid status,
electrolyte balance,
and acid-base balance.
We'll talk about
every single one of
those over the next
series of lectures.
And then finally, it's
got an important hormonal
responsibility. It's a
production and activation of
hormones involved in the
formation of red blood cells,
in calcium metabolism,
and control of blood
pressure and flow.
So it's linked to
hematology, it's linked
to bone formation,
muscle, bone and muscle
metabolism, and cardiovascular
cardiovascular events. So
you've taken anatomy, so
you all know it's a pair
of bean-shaped structures
the size of your fist that
lie behind the peritoneum
on each side of the
vertebral column. It's small.
It's only about 0.5% of
the total body weight.
obviously, you know,
men are are heavier
than average men are
heavier than average
females, so men have a
slightly larger kidney.
Then
we can start off with the
hylas indicated in the
circle here, and the hylas
is indicated here, here,
and that's the site
of entry for the renal
artery, indicated
in the red, and the
renal vein, indicated
here in the blue, and
the entrance and the
exit of the tubules.
The renal artery
breaks up into anterior
-posterior branches, and then
these anterior-posterior
branches will eventually
give rise to the
arcuate and then the
interlobular arteries.
So they do different things.
The arcuate arteries,
one, they skirt the
corticomedullary junction, and
then they branch into the
ascending interlobular
arteries, which will
eventually give us the apparent
arterioles when we get
into the arteriolar system.
The renal sinus seen here
includes the pelvis and
urine-filled spaces called
the calluses, the major and
the minor, And they're all
surrounded by renal
parenchymal cells, except where
you reach the upper end of
the ureter, the top part
of the kidney, which is
seen probably around here.
A fibrous capsule covers
each kidney, and this capsule
eventually will reflect
into the hilus at this,
you know, in these
junctions here.
And the inner layers
will eventually
coat the renal sinus, and
the outer layers will give
us the, you know, blood
vessels and renal pelvis.
Grossly, if you cross,
you know, you divide the
kidney into two equal
halves, and basically
across a longitudinal
cross section, excuse
me, I had a mental block,
You can differentiate
just based on their color,
the cortex and the
medulla. The cortex is a
granular outer region
through the presence of
glomeruli and highly
convoluted tubules. These
are not macroscopic.
These are not microscopic.
They're macroscopy.
You can actually
see the glomeruli
if you look really,
really closely.
The medulla is a darker
inner region. it lacks
gourmet airline and
where you have parallel
arrangements of tubules
of small blood vessels,
and it's divided into
renal pyramids. And these
pyramids face the
corticomedullary border
and the tip will terminate
in the renal pelvis.
The vasculature of
the kidney is where
everybody starts having
some issues because it's
got a very atypical
and unique vasculature.
So kidneys have very high
blood flow and there is, you
know, for what did we say,
it's for the small proportion
of the total body weight,
they take one of the
largest amounts of blood
flow from the heart, about 20
-25% of the cardiac output,
almost a quarter, fifth to
a quarter of our cardiac
output goes to our kidneys.
And this high blood
flow is important.
It provides the blood
plasma necessary
to form the ultrafiltrate.
Now the renal circulation, once
you go away from
the renal artery,
goes into two different
systems. It starts off with the
first arteriolar system,
the afferent arteriole. The
afferent arteriole is a
high-resistance arteriolar
network bringing blood into
the glomerulus. So I have it
here indicated as AA, so it
goes into the glomerulus.
Glomerulus is a high
-pressure capillary
network, and its
function is filtration.
Then, as opposed to
other tissue organs,
where you can go from
arterial to capillary,
then to venial,
and then to veins,
kidney is different. Kidney
will go from arteriolar
to capillary, and then
back to arteriolar,
the efferent arteriolar system.
And these are second
high pressure,
in high, excuse me, high
resistance arterioles.
The pressure is not as
high, right, because this is
one of the functions of
glomeruli, so dissipate the
pressure, use the pressure
to push the ultrafiltrate.
But the apparent arteriole
is high resistance.
It can manipulate its
resistance to a high degree.
And then after that,
we have peritubular
capillaries, which is our
low-pressure capillary
networks surrounding the
renal tubules. And that's
mostly in the cortex, if
you go further deeper into
the kidney, before you get
to the medulla, you get
to the juxtamedullary
area, juxtamedullary, the
corticomedullary, there
you can have juxtamedullary
glomeruli, at or near the
medullary cortical junction.
then the difference
here is the peritubular
capillaries of these
nephrons descend into the
renal papilla to give
these hairpin-shaped
vessels called the vasorecta.
And here's an example
of vasorecta here.
So, you know, in this
case, it's, you know,
peritubular capillaries.
Vasorecta would be
the capillaries you
see here. We'll talk
about the vasorecta
later on, in one of
our later lectures.
So 90% of the blood
entering the kidney perfuses
the superficial glomeruli
and the cortex, and 10%
perfuse the juxtaglomeruli
and the medulla. So you can
see right off the bat that
there's unequal perfusion.
This makes the juxtamedullary
glomeruli and the
medulla, relatively anoxic
compared to the superficial
glomerula and the
cortex. And that becomes
very, very important later
on when we talk about control
of erythropoietin and
red blood cell formation.
And then finally, we have
lymphatic vessels that
drain cortical interstitial
fluid and contain
the renal hormones, such
as erythropoietin, and
they leave the kidney
following the arteries
toward the hilus, and they
don't, you know, these
lymphatic vessels are
really found in the
cortex, and they're absent
from the renal medulla.
The functional unit
of the kidney is the
nephron, and we have
about a million of them,
you know, anywhere
between 800,000 to 1.2
million nephrons per
kidney. That actually is
relatively equal
in male and female
kidneys. Interesting
enough, that number
is also similar in
different species.
So rats have about a million
nephrons, which always
puzzles them because
their kidneys are this
big compared to ours, which
is the size of a fist.
But each nephron consists
of a glomerulus and a
tubule, and this schematic
here that I made kind of
indicates that glomeruli
coming from the afferent
arterial leaving through
the efferent arteriole, the
glomerular capillaries,
and then the epithelial
structures that constitute
the nephron. So each nephron
is independent until it
reaches the collecting
tubules, and you can see
that here, different nephrons
will all result in the
same, end up in the same
collecting ducts. So
there are two populations
of nephrons within the
renal cortex. We have
superficial nephrons,
which have very short loops
extending to the boundary
between the outer
and inner medulla. And
as I mentioned before,
the juxtamedullary nephrons
that are associated
with juxtamedullary
glomeruli, and they play a
special role in her
production of concentrated
urine, with long loops
extending into the medulla.
So initially, we have
the renal corpuscle,
and this is the renal
corpuscle is here,
consists of the glomerulus
and the Bowman's capsule.
It's the cytoformation
of the glomerular
filtrate, compromising
of the glomerulus,
tubule, and Bowman's capsule,
the glomerular capsule.
I should have
mentioned the tubule
associated with that,
so this whole thing is
constitutes that. The
tubular glomerulus is a
cluster of capillaries
from which plasma
filtrate originates. Our
tubules are epithelial
structures. They're
subdivided into different
histologically and
functionally distinct sections.
You can detect them under
normal histology and
under EEM very clearly.
And then we have Bowman's
capsule, the glomerular
capsule up here. It's
an epithelial structure
surrounding the glomerulus.
And inside the Bowman's
capsule, in between the
two epithelial layers,
we have Bowman's space.
Bowman's space becomes
contiguous with the lumen
of the nephron. What comes
out of the glomerulus
into Bowman's space
is the ultrafiltrate,
and what comes out of
the nephron is urine. So
you go from plasma to
ultrafiltrate to urine.
And Bowman's space,
obviously, is the
space between the
parietal layer, the
inner layer, and
glomerular capillaries.
Embryologically, the
urinary system is derived
from the uretric bud from
the collecting duct to
the ureters. The tubular
epithelium between
Bowman's capsule and the
connecting ducts arise from
condensed mesenchymal
cells, and the proximal
end of the tubular
epithelium, which is the
proximal tubules, attaches
to the vascular bundle
that develops into the
glomerular capillary tuft.
The thinning of one
end of the epithelium
leads to the emergence
of the parietal layer.
So this is the parietal layer,
right? The ones that
surrounds Bowman's capsule.
And the other side
will thicken and just
attach to the
glomerular capillaries.
These visceral epithelial
cells will later fold
into cells called podocytes,
and you can see them
here in this EM. They sit
on top of capillaries.
You can see them attached here,
right,
the EM. And these podocytes are
modified epithelial
cells. Remember,
like pericytes.
Again, they represent the
visceral layer of Bowman's
capsule, and they're continuous
with the parietal layer
of Bowman's capsule. They
have contractile ability.
So they're epithelial cells
with contractile elements.
And as I said before,
ultrafiltrate will
drain from Bowman's
capsule into the tubule
and into the proximal
tubule and then further
into the nephron.
Coming out of the glomerulus
has to go through the
glomerular filtration barrier.
So what is the glomerular
filtration barrier? So in
a mature kidney, one of the
things that we see are
the podocytes covering the
glomerular capillaries. And
this EM shows that very nicely.
You can see the cell body
in purple and of one. You
can see the cell body of
another one in green. So you
can see that their foot
processes interdigitate with
each other. So if the
glomerulus is inside my hands,
you can say that each
hand is one protocyte, and
they will go around the
glomerulus and creating a
network of projections of
endothelial cells, the glomerular
endothelial cells will
secrete the glycocalyx.
These are negatively
charged glycosaminoglycans,
and this deposition is
a charge barrier, so it
prevents the leakage of
large negatively charged
macromolecules. The endothelial
cells are fenestrated,
very large fenestration.
They're not sinusoidal,
they're still fenestrated,
but large fenestrations,
and they don't have any
restrictions to either
water, small solutes,
electrolytes, and small
proteins out of the capillary,
peptides specifically.
And the basement membrane
between the endothelial
cells and the protocyte
has three layers, the inner
thinner layer, the thick
layer, and the outer thinner
layer. And they also
contain the heparan sulfate
proteoglycans. So the basement
membrane and the glycocalyx
together form a very
large negatively charged
net that stops the filtration
of negatively charged
proteins and any cell
that's trying to get into
glomerular space because
they have the cell membrane,
the phospholipids will give
it a net negative charge.
So the podocytes, again,
they have, you know,
they have put processes
that give you secondary,
primary and secondary
processes that are
linked to the cell body.
These are called petty
cells. You can actually
see the petty cells and
you can actually see
them under EM, but under
the EM, you can really
see the distinction
between the fenestrations
indicated here.
Where did my...
Fenestrations are...
Sorry. You can see
the fenestrated
endothelium here,
and the pedicels are
these foot processes
that stick out.
They are connected
by slit diagrams,
diaphragms, excuse me.
These are filtration slits, and
they are controlled. They have
diaphragms that can
manipulate their
width anywhere from
4 to 14 nanometers.
And then you have
a lot of large
negatively charged
glycoproteins
that cover the
protocyte cell body.
And again, these contribute to
the restriction
of large anions.
So it's important the
integrity of the slit diaphragm
and the PETI cells are
maintained by a number of
different integral membrane
proteins, such as nephrin-1,
neph-1, also known as
Curel1 and Potosin.
Why are these
important? Well, they
can be manipulated
by phosphorylation
and they can change
permeability according to
phosphorylation. And any
kind of defect or damage to
these proteins can make
the barriers leaky and
result in the appearance
of large proteins, such as
albumin in the urines.
So, for example, nephrotic
syndrome is an example
of one that a defect in
these proteins leads to
albumin in ultrafiltrate.
Mesangial cells are
incredibly important. Unlike
potocytes, they originate
from embryonic mesangial
cells, and they're integral
to maintaining structural
integrity of the glomerular
microvasculature.
They're smooth muscle-like.
They are more like smooth
muscle than they are like
epithelial cells, even
though they are still not
considered to be vascular
smooth muscle cells. They
have a lot of similarities,
but they have contractile
properties similar to
vascular smooth muscle cells.
and compounds that affect
vascular smooth muscle
cells and the arterioles
will usually have the same
effects on mesangial cells.
Their main role is to
influence glomerular filtration
rate by regulating blood
flow of the glomerular
capillaries or by altering
the capillary surface
area, right, affecting
filtration coefficient. They
also are important in
secreting the extracellular
matrix, and they have
phagocytic activity by removing
macromolecules from
mesangium and getting rid of
them. So they kind of have
a macrophage-like phenotype
and vascular smooth muscle
cell-like phenotype.
And they secrete a
variety of different
autocrine and
paracrine mediators,
such as prostaglandins
and cytokines.
You can find mesangial
cells also outside of the
glomerular, extra-glomerular
mesangial cells. And these
are found outside of the
glomerular, right? It's
very easy. If it's extra
-glomerular, you can find
them outside the glomerulus.
They're usually found
between the afferent and
efferent arterioles and they
interact with an area, a
specialized area near the
glomerulus called the
macula densa. These are
specialized tubular epithelial
cells and they're granular
cells and they form
a complex called the
juxtaglomerular apparatus.
And the JGA, we'll go into its
functions later on, is one
of the components of the
mechanisms known for
maintaining homeostasis by
activating the tubular
glomerular feedback mechanism.
How about the tubular
components of the nephron?
So they're derived
from the uretric bud
and metanephrine
blastema, and this is the
epithelial structure
that creates urine.
I have it indicated here
on the right-hand side.
I have it indicated also
in urine in yellow to
kind of give it the idea
that this is where we
have urine and what color
and the role it does.
So again, Bowman's capsule,
glomerular capsule,
surrounds the glomerulus
and contains Bowman's
space. First thing out of
the Bowman's capsule are
the proximal tubules.
Proximal tubules are divided
into three segments based
on their appearance.
The first section,
macroscopically, you can
detect it. It's the
proximal convoluted
tubule. You can naturally
see it wind around.
It's also broken down
into three sections, and
sections one and two, S1
and S2, constitute the
proximal convoluted tubule.
These are, they have
extensive microvilli
and some in their apical
site. Remember, these
are all epithelial cells,
so they're highly polar.
They have basolateral and
apical. Apical faces
the urine, the lumen,
inside of the nephron, and
the basolateral sits on
the basement membrane and
faces the interstitial.
They are extremely
mitochondria-rich. In fact,
you know, I've actually
looked at them under
the electron microscope.
You can compare the density
of their mitochondria to
energetic tissues like
the heart. So they're
really an important source
of energy for the function
that they have. And then
you have at the terminal
end of the proximal tubule,
you'll have the proximal
straight tubule, PST.
And this is the last
part of the S2 and the S3
sections. These cells have
diminished ultrastructural
complexity compared to
proximal convoluted tubule.
From there, you go to
the thin descending
limb, and the thin
descending limb,
then you go into the loop
of Henle, and then to
the thin ascending limb.
The thin descending
and thin ascending limbs
are less complex and
have flatter cells than
the proximal convoluted
tubule, either sections of it.
After the thin ascending,
so now we were going,
you know, there's a
directionality that we
have to follow here.
So, you know, we've gone
this way and now we're
going this way and now
we're coming back up and
now we are here, right?
So the thick ascending
limb of the loop of Henley,
tau.
These cells also have
tall interdigitations,
and they're also
energetically rich in
invaginated basolateral
membranes, when
you see them under the
electron microscope.
Then we proceed to the
distal convoluted tubule,
here again convoluted,
and then into the cortical
collecting duct and the
medullary collecting ducts.
And the distal convoluted
tubule, the cells
are similar to the
thick ascending limb
morphologically.
They respond to
different drugs and
they have different
channel profiles,
transporter profiles.
And then the cortical
collecting duct has got two
very unique sets of cells
called the principal and
intercalated cells. And we'll
go over that when we talk
about some of the functionality
of these sections.
And this is some EM of
proximal convoluted tubule,
S1, S2, and S3. You can
see that the length of
the brush border is higher
in S1 compared to S2.
you can see the high
number of mitochondria.
These are all mitochondria
that you see here.
You know, I mean, you
probably have to find better
ways than to visually
compare the two, but these
are also a little bit
shorter, and the brush
border is not as elaborate
as you can find in the
PCT, but again, we don't
want to really go that
much into the histological
distinctions. Remember,
they face the lumen,
which is very important.
So what are some of the
functional distinction between
the sections of the nephron?
Well, let's start off
with the proximal tubule,
right? Proximal convoluted
tubule up here, right?
proximal convoluted tubule.
So once the ultrafiltrate
is absorbed, is created
in the glomerulus,
the job of the nephron
is to take almost
everything that can be used
that's usable and necessary
back into the body.
That means 67% of the
filtered water and
electrolytes are reabsorbed
together, water and
electrolytes. So this is
an isoosmotic reabsorption.
Also, it reabsorbs
almost all the glucose
proteins, amino
acids, and most of the
bicarbonate that's found
in the ultrafiltrate.
This section is highly
permeable to water due to the
non-regulated expression
of aquaporin-1 in the
apical and basolateral
membranes. So you have
a heavy driving force and
you have high permeability.
So water goes right
through these cells.
Thin descending limb
of the loop of Henle
and the thin ascending
limbs of loop of
Henle, they are
relatively impermeable to
solutes, but they are
permeable to water.
So water is reabsorbed,
about 15% of
it reabsorbed in
the thin descending
limb, also mediated
by aquaporins. Um,
what is, what results
in the ultrafiltrate
as it, uh, enters, leaves
the thin ascending,
descending and
ascending and reaches
the thick section is
a very concentrated
ultrafiltrate,
right? Because we've
gotten rid of water
and we keep the salts.
So it's got higher
concentration than
you would find in
the proximal tubule.
You get to the thick
ascending limb, then it flips.
It's impermeable to water.
So water does not cross
the thick ascending limb
of the loop of Henle.
It is incredibly permeable
to sodium, chloride,
and potassium,
magnesium,
and calcium.
So sodium chloride is
absorbed, potassium is both
reabsorbed and then
secreted, and we'll go into
the distinctions later
on, through transport
mechanisms. So these are
transported via transporters.
Magnesium and
calcium are absorbed
parasailally, so they
go in between the cells.
And, you know, so if
the cells are, you know,
if These are the
thick ascending cells.
This is the lumen. This
is the interstitium.
Calcium and magnesium
will go in between,
not through these cells to
get to the interstitium.
and then whatever is left
of the bicarb that's not
reabsorbed in the proximal
tubule is reabsorbed
in the thick ascending
limb. And then the distal
convoluted tubule and the
collecting ducts reabsorb
around 8% of the remaining
sodium chloride and
they secrete variable
amounts of either protons,
hydrogen ions, or potassium,
depending on different
stimuli. And the water is
also reabsorbed to a varying
degree, again, based on
regulation by hormones.
So by the time you get
to the urine, you have
basically reabsorbed
almost all the sodium,
all the chloride, all
the glucose, all the
amino acids, the
majority of proteins, and
anything. And what's
left is basically water,
a little bit of salt, and waste
products like urea
and uric acid.
So, the solute and
permeabilities are different
in each section of the
nephron. And this is a
very, very broad viewpoint
of it, breaking down.
And the numbers indicate
the osmolarities in
the tubule as you're
going through the nephron.
So the kidneys are
amazing. They are
capable of producing
a high range of
osmolalities in the
urine, from high to low.
And they'll do that
based on different
permeabilities and
different functions.
And this is just general.
Again, you know, we'll
go through specifics later
on and how they do it.
Proximal tubule water
reabsorption is paracellular,
while solute reabsorption is
transcellular and paracellular.
If you go back to the
last lecture to get the
distinction between trans
and para, I suggest you do.
Thin descending limb
of loop of Henle,
water reabsorption
is paracellular,
solid reabsorption is minimal,
so there's almost none,
so it's not really considered
to be that important.
in the thin ascending
loop of Henle.
There's very little
water reabsorption, but
solute reabsorption is
paracellular. There's
some water reabsorption,
just not as much as
you would find in the
thin descending limb.
This gets reinforced in
the thick ascending limb,
where again, you have
absolutely no water
reabsorption. And solute
reabsorption, as I indicated
before, is both transcellular
and paracellular.
Distal tubule, you
don't have any water
reabsorption, and the
solute reabsorption is
all paracellular. And
the collecting duct,
the water reabsorption
is transcellular,
again via aquaporins,
every time,
and solute reabsorption is
transcellular and paracellular.
And
I'm going to correct myself
and add both transcellular
and paracellular to
the proximal tubule. I
apologize for missing that
out. I don't want to give
you a false message, you
know, conflicting messages,
because I did mention
that there are aquaporins,
and they contribute to
transcellular movement.
The JG apparatus, as I like
to call the juxtaglomerular
apparatus, it's not me,
everybody calls them that,
consists of extra
glomerular mesangial cells,
the macula densa, and
granular cells. And the macula
densa is a patch of
specialized tubular
epithelial cells at the
transition of the collecting
duct, distal collecting
duct, and the thick
ascending limb. And it
contacts the glomerulus that
is bound to the nephron.
These cells have large nuclei
that are closely packed.
I indicated it here. So,
you know, this is how we
usually indicate the nephron,
right? But but really,
the ultra structure is a
little bit different. If you
look here, you can see that
the glomeruli here kind of
loops in or is here and the
distal convoluted tubule
loops in and interacts with
the afferent arterioles
and the glomerulus itself.
And this little area here
is the macula densa, right?
This area here becomes the
macula densa. And you can
see it here. The granular
cells are very, very clear
because they have granules
in them. And these granules
are packed with an enzyme
called renin. And I will
talk about renin in a couple
of cells. They're specialized
smooth muscle cells.
They store and release
the enzyme renin.
The JGA is part the
feedback mechanism that
directly regulates
renal blood flow and
filtration rates and
indirectly modulates
sodium balance and
systemic blood pressure.
And the two main
roles, the first one is
tubular glomerular
feedback, and that's the
regulation of glomerular
filtration rate
depending on water and
sodium chloride load reaching
the macula densa. So the
more macula, the more the
macula densa senses a higher
load. A higher load to the
macula densa means
less water, so it
stimulates processes
to retain water,
vice versa. If it's too
dilute, it stops it, so
you end up losing more
water to maintain the
balance. It also controls
renal blood flow, detects
changes in the pressure
of the renal artery
via baroreceptors in the
afferent arterioles to
regulate the renin-angiotensin
aldosterone system.
So it's pronounced
renin in the dictionary.
That's how it's pronounced.
Some people pronounce
renin. It's wrong.
Do not pronounce it
renin. It's renin.
so make sure that you
pronounce it correctly.
The innervation is by the
sympathetic nervous system.
There is no parasympathetic
nervous system
innervation in the
kidney. It is a
unique system. It's
one of the unique
systems that you
only get sympathetic.
The three major effects
are vasoconstriction,
enhanced sodium reabsorption
by proximal tubule, and
stimulation of renin
secretion by norepinephrine.
Again, this is normal
autonomic physiology.
Norepinephrine will act on
our arteries, arterioles, on
smooth muscle cells,
specifically alpha-1 receptors
to cause vasoconstriction.
It acts on alpha-1, alpha
-2 receptors on proxima
tubular cells to enhance
sodium reabsorption, and
beta-1 receptors on granular
cells on the JG apparatus
to stimulate renin. It's
got afferent innervation.
The afferents are sensory
fibers. They detect
baroreceptor and chemoreceptor
influences to maintain
perfusion pressure and
make sure that our electrolyte
balances are normal.
And of course, it's got
pain receptors for injury.
The other important
section that we have to be
aware about is the role of
kidney as an endocrine organ.
So it produces
renin, it produces
vitamin D and erythropoietin.
Paracrine, it produces
bradykinin and prostaglandins
that can act locally to
control local circulation.
The definitions are here.
Renin, I'll start off with
that. We'll go back to
the renin and its role in
later slides. But as an
introduction, it's an enzyme,
also called angiotensinogenase,
commonly known as renin.
It's an enzyme that
initiates the renin
-angiotensin-aldosterone system.
and it's a plasma protein
30 to 50 kilodalton plasma
protein and what it does
it by definition right
it's an angiotensinogenase it
metabolizes angiotensinogen
which is a liver protein
a big one it's an
alpha 1 globulin 452
amino acids i don't expect
anybody to memorize amino
acids by the way. Just know
the generalities and, you
know, and what they mean,
right? So renin is released
in the plasma. What
it will do, it will cleave
off a 10 amino acid piece
of angiotensinogen, and
that's angiotensin 1.
Angiotensin 1 has no biological
activity. It requires
conversion by an enzyme called
angiotensin converting enzyme.
Angiotensin converting enzyme
is found on the endothelial
surface of the cardiovascular
system. However,
a lot of the times you
will hear saying that this
conversion occurs in the
lung. And that's more, that
has more to do with how the
blood flow is regulated.
As we said, what percentage
of, you know, I'm not
asking Socratic questions in
a Zoom session, excuse me.
We said that kidneys get
20-25% of cardiac output,
right? So 20-25% of the
cardiac output comes
out, goes into the
kidney, will come back
out, out of the veins.
So the two kidneys
will bring back
20-25 percent of
the total blood volume, right?
The rest of the systems
are feeding into that.
So when our venous
return was going back
into our heart, um, is
now a mix of different
blood from different, uh,
tissues. One of
them has got rena,
and now we want to metabolize,
and who's been, that's got
angiotensin 1. So what we
want to do is make sure
that all the angiotensin 1
is metabolized into
angiotensin 2. And the best
place for it to do that is in
the lungs. Because remember,
our blood comes from
the veins into the right
side of the heart, comes
out of the right ventricle,
and 100% of the blood output
for each beat comes out
and goes into the lungs.
So it's a really great
way to get angiotensin II,
which is the effector molecule
of the renin-angiotensin
system. What does Ang
II do? Well, it stimulates
sodium reabsorption,
vasoconstriction, elastone
secretion, and antidiuretic
hormone secretion, and will
go into its physiology.
It also is integral for
the formation of vitamin
D, even though vitamin
D is sort of a misnomer.
It's not really a vitamin,
right? It's a vitamin,
if you don't know the
history, vital amines.
They were usually aminergic
compounds that had
an amino group. We don't
have that on vitamin D.
It's actually a fat-soluble
secosteroid hormone,
and it promotes calcium
conversion in the body.
It does it two ways,
intestinal calcium
absorption, reducing
calcium loss.
And it's ingested and
produced, the precursors are
produced by the actions of
ultraviolet light on your skin
right that's basically what
everybody says go stand
in the sun you will get your
vitamin d you know um you
don't need that much of it
believe it or not they say
10 to 15 minutes a day is
usually good enough um but it
is formed from cholesterol
and from the pathways to
form cholesterol even
though it's not derived from
cholesterol let's derive from
a precursor of cholesterol.
7-dehydrocholesterol,
which is found in the skin.
UV sunlight
gives us vitamin
D3, and vitamin
D3 is in turn metabolized to
25-hydroxyvitamin D and
then to dihydroxy 1,
25-dihydroxyvitamin D,
which is the functional
vitamin.
And its conversion is under
the control of parathyroid
hormone. And vitamin D
acts on vitamin D receptors
throughout the body. It's
another interesting story.
We're not going to go that
much into it. But it's
got its own receptors. It
has signaling capabilities.
And the last component
of the endocrine kidney
would be erythropoietin.
Now going to talking
about erythropoietin
next semester, but as an
introduction, it is the
most important regulator
in the proliferation of
erythroid progenitors
and the production
of red blood cells.
So it stimulates the
proliferation and maturation
of progenitors to give us
red blood cells in the bone
marrow. This was the
first human hematopoietic
growth factor to be isolated,
and it made Amgen rich.
In humans,
especially in adults,
actually let's do
that the other way, in
adult humans, 90% is
produced in kidneys,
in these cells that
are called peritubular
interstitial cells. Another
10 percent in parasinusoidal
cells in the liver, and
they respond to changes in
tissue oxygen content to
make EPO, but I'll go into
the full detail in that
later on. So they are
responsive to hypoxia, and
this cartoon here gives us a
nice little example of how
hypoxia actually increases
the number of EPO-producing
cells in the kidney.
A component of the
paracrine kidney is the
kyninogen or the
calocrine system. You can
think of this as a
parallel system to the
renin-angiotensin system
because they share
this guy here, angiotensin
-converting enzyme.
These things were
discovered at the same time.
The difference is while
angiotensin-converting
enzyme activates
angiotensin-1 for
the final effector
molecule, angiotensin-2,
the kininogen calocrine
system's effective mediator
is bradykinin, And
angiotensin-converting enzyme
breaks down bradykinin
into inactive fragments. In
fact, it was initially called
bradykinin-potentiating
enzyme until they found
out that bradykinin
-potentiating enzyme and
angiotensin-converting enzyme
were the exact same molecule.
So bradykinin can act
directly on tubular cells
in the nephron to reduce
sodium reabsorption,
but it also stimulates
endothelial cells to release
nitric oxide and different
products of arachidonic
acid to regulate naturesis
and dilation of blood
vessels in the glomerulus.
And then finally we come
to the ureter and the
bladder, so by the time
we get to the most distal
portion of the collecting
duct, the filtrate
is the urine. There is
no modification of that
in the pelvis,
ureter, bladder, and
urethra. So once it
leaves, enters the
urine, the renal
pelvis, it is done.
The ureters obviously serve
as a conduit for the passage
of urine from the urine
pelvis to the bladder,
right? So the ureters connect
the kidney to the bladder
and then the bladder, and
then the bladder, excuse me,
the outflow of the
bladder is the urethra.
In men, it goes in
between the prostate and
then ends in the
genitalia for urination.
Luminar beach ureter is
lined by transitional
epithelium. If you, you
know, hopefully you've taken
a look at the histology,
you can see that it's
very, very interesting
in terms of its ability
to go from very complex
epithelial to a straightforward
tuboidal epithelial based on
how much filling there is.
And it is a syncytium.
I can't even pronounce
that. I'm sorry. I
usually could pronounce
it, but I have,
whatchamacallit, Invisalign,
so I'm kind of
lisping a little bit.
Peristalsis in the
urethral originates from
pacemaker cells in the
proximal portion of the renal
pelvis, and this is a
stimulus for urination.
Autonomic nervous
system can modulate the
peristalsis, but
that's not an absolute
requirement. You all
kind of know that.
Sometimes you have
to urinate, but other
times you can control
your urination.
And the sympathetic nervous
system via a variety
of different plexi enhance
urethral contractility.
The main portion of the
bladder that collects urine
and funnel-shaped neck
that connects with urethra
is that's considered to be
the bladder the lumen as
i said is is lined by
transitional epithelium um
it's got three poorly layered
uh of of smooth muscle
uh detrestle muscles and
these lack a cap gap junction
so they don't act as a
syncytium um at the lower
trip at the lower tip
of of the ladder the the
bladder the la the bladder
opens up into the urethra
and they are controlled
of the muscles by two
different sphincters,
internal and external
sphincters.
We have sympathetic
nervous system innervation
on these things, on
these sphincters,
and they start off
from lumbar splantic
nerves going to the
hypogastric plexus
and then ending
up in the distal
portion of the
hypogastric nerve.
And parasympathetic
intervasion, so
unlike the kidney,
we do have both.
Ganglia is the
intermediate cell column,
and preganglionic is
the pre-pelvic-splantic
nerve, and goes to
postganglionic neurons that go
to the body and neck. And
then we have pneumotor
neurons that also control
bladder contractility
coming from S2 and S4
of your spine and motor
neuron ganglias in the
central nervous system.
And finally, talk a
little bit about bladder
tone. So bladder tone
is defined by its
relationship between
volume and pressure, and it
can be measured. It's
actually a diagnostic,
you can use diagnostically
by a systometrogram.
So we'll break it down.
If you look at the basal
systometrogram here in the
solid line. I've broken
it down into three sections,
A, B, and C. So let's
start off with A. So if
we have an increase in
bladder volume, and this
is anywhere between 0 to
50 mLs, we see a moderately
steep increase in
pressure in the initial
sections, right, in the first
50. But the other parts,
by the time we get to 100
mL, we don't have any
changes in pressure. So it's
a steep increase in
pressure and then it stops.
And then as the
volume increases,
it goes above
that 50 mL, right,
into around 300 mL, you get
almost no pressure increase.
And this reflects a
relaxation of bladder smooth
muscle, right? The more fluid
comes, the bigger it gets.
And then at volumes over
400 ml, right? And you
have here in C, you have
a massive increase in
pressure. So bladder tone
in this case is up to
its maximal amount.
And at this point, this
amount triggers the
micturition reflex.
And this reflex is
independent of any
kind of innervations,
right? You don't
need innervation in
order to urinate.
Normally, it's inhibited by
the biocenters in the
pontine nucleus, by the urge.
And the urge for voluntary
bladder emptying starts
like around halfway through
B, 150 mLs. And then the
voiding phase comes with
a voluntary relaxions of
the external sphincter,
followed by relaxation of the
internal sphincter and
these afferent signals are
sent when a small amount of
urine reaches the proximal
urethra. And this is
something you've experienced.
If you urinate a little
bit, the urge to urinate a
lot is almost immediate
and it's difficult to stop.
So and the myctoturition
reflex is there's no
any, there's no longer
any inhibition from the
PMC to the parasympathetic
and everything just
relaxes. The bladder will,
the sphincters relax,
the bladder contracts
and urine is expelled.
And the initial
bladder contraction
sensory impulses from
stretch receptors and
establishes self
-regeneration process.
So indication I have
here, the Cysto-Metrogram,
the CMG, the diagnostic
test that can measure
bladder pressure, capacity,
and muscle function. So
basically what it
is, is insertion
of a catheter
through the urethra,
emptying the bladder and
then adding increments
of water and seeing what
the responses are. So
50 ml increments of water
until you reach a point
and see where this process
will get activated.
And it kind of gives
you an indication
on its capacity to respond to
central nervous system.
And finally, let's
go back. Why did
that young lady
have this problem?
Well, this is a real
story, actually.
The herbal tea that she
had ordered consisted
of a lot of lookalikes
that had this very,
very toxic compound called
aristocolic acid. And
aristocolic acid causes
acute kidney injury.
And this was a
dramatic effect. It was
observed in a number
of people who had gone,
who had this tea, who
ended up needing dialysis
and kidney transplants
because it was such
a, so much damage was
to their kidneys. these.
Anyway,
thank you and I'll talk
to you and you'll hear
from me in two or three
lectures. You have a
couple of scholars coming
up for the next two
lectures. Thank you and
we'll see you around.